<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some reflections upon the Earl of Danby, in relation to the murther of Sir Edmondbury Godfrey in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>J. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229770</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153044</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76175)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153044)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2342:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some reflections upon the Earl of Danby, in relation to the murther of Sir Edmondbury Godfrey in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>J. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: J.B.</note>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, there is a comma after the word "Godfrey" on the title page. In the edition at reel 756:14, there is a period after "Godfrey".</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Leeds, Thomas Osborne, --  Duke of, 1631-1712 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Godfrey, Edmund Berry, --  Sir, 1621-1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153044:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>SOME REFLECTIONS Upon the Earl of DANBY, In Relation to the MURTHER of <hi>Sir Edmondbury Godfrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In a Letter to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Do in all Sincerity and Chriſtian Love, give you the trouble of theſe Lines, that you nor the reſt of your Friends at a diſtance, may not be altogether ignorant of the Cauſes which have prevented the Good we expected by the late Seſſions of Parliament, which has ended ſo ſurprizingly, indeed to the amazement and trouble of all Parties, except ſome few concerned in the Black Counſels, and Dark Deſigns have of late been taken: ſuch perſons will with all Induſtry imaginable ſeek to ſpread abroad, That the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy of the Houſe of Commons for the Tryal of the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> before the Five Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Lords, and excluding the Biſhops from having any Votes therein, contrary to the Judgment of the Lords, made their continuance unpracticable; which though perhaps true, as things have been manag'd, yet if the Reaſons (which are here incloſed) be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and the Grounds for thoſe Reaſons (taken in their Secret Committee) be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they could not but proceed in the method they did, except they would betray the Truſt repoſed in them, by ſuffering the great Incendiary and Poiſon of the Nation to eſcape in the dark, whilſt Flouds of others Bloud (and perhaps ſome of Innocents) muſt have been let out, to Hoodwinck the People from diſcerning the true cauſe of the decay of Trade, and other dangers and miſeries they at preſent lye under. Therefore the better to clear things to you, I have <hi>verbatim</hi> tranſcribed a Paper ſent to divers Parliament-men, and examin'd in the Secret Committee of Commons, which is in theſe words following.</p>
            <p>IT is generally thought, and there is great reaſon to believe, that other perſons were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Murder of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> than have been yet brought upon the Stage. Now to find who theſe are likely to be, the Rule of Dr. <hi>Lloyd</hi> in his Funeral Sermon, in <hi>Caſius</hi> his words, is the moſt proper way, <hi>Cui bono? For whoſe Intereſt was it?</hi> if without partiality we can be guided by that Rule.</p>
            <p>Therefore not to find faults with others in their gueſſes, I will take leave to enquire by ſome Matter of Fact, whether the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> had not as much reaſon to wiſh him out of the World, as any Papiſt? And then by the ſame way to enquire, whether he was not as likely to have it in his Power to do it? And laſtly, whether by ſome ſtrong Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances he was not willing to put that Power in Act? leaving the proof of all to the Inquiry of ſuch as are in Authority to do it.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153044:2"/>
            <p>Firſt, I am confident it is not hard to prove, that Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrry</hi> when he took the Examinations from Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> and Dr. <hi>Tongue,</hi> did require of them by the Oath or O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> they or any of them had taken, to tell him whether the Buſineſs had not been reveal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by them to any other Perſon, before that time.</p>
            <p>To which after ſome diſputes between them, whether they were bound to anſwer ſuch Queſtions; Firſt, they did comply and acknowledge, that it had been made known to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Lord Treaſurer a long time before.</p>
            <p>He then required the punctual time and place: To all which Queſtions he had Anſwers proper.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It will be as eaſie to prove, that all this Tranſaction he immediately made known to Mr. <hi>Coleman,</hi> who at his requeſt went to <hi>Windſor</hi> to inform the Duke of it.</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe certain, that the Duke immediately let the King know of it, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged he had had a former account of the Plot, and had told the Lord Treaſurer the ſame, whom he believed had never heard of it but from himſelf.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain that my Lord <hi>Danby</hi> did always pretend both to the King, and the Duke, he never had heard of it, till from his Majeſty; when 'tis as certain he had correſpondence with Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> and Dr. <hi>Tongue,</hi> by the means of Mr. <hi>Kirby</hi> a Merchant, Brother to Col. <hi>Kirby,</hi> long before the time he pretended to have heard of it from the King.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> was the perſon who ſent the Duke the firſt account of the Plot; he likewiſe let Mr. <hi>Coleman</hi> know from time to time all he could gather of it, and it can be proved by many witneſſes, that they had divers private Meetings to conſult about ſomthing, during the King's reſiding at <hi>Windſor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Duke came back, Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> attended him, deſiring to know his pleaſure concerning the News he had ſent him by Mr. <hi>Coleman.</hi> The Duke told him, he had told the Lord Treaſurer of it: At which Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> ſeem'd extremely trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, becauſe he found the Lord Treaſurer did not deſire to have it known, being he heard of it long before.</p>
            <p>It is well known, Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> after this received ſeveral ſevere expreſſions, and much ill language from the Lord <hi>Danby,</hi> of which he complained to divers Perſons of Quality, particularly in <hi>Danby</hi>'s Houſe, when he waited to ſpeak with him the very mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that day on which he is ſaid to be Murthered.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> had reaſon to fear the King and Dukes Anger, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the diſcovery ſo long before made to him, and that he was willing to keep them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an opinion he knew nothing of it, till he had it from his Majeſty; Then who had he ſo much reaſon to wiſh out of the way, as Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey?</hi> who had revealed the truth to the Duke, and who was beſt able by the Examinations he had taken, to make the certainty of it appear to the Parliament, the meeting of whom at that time ſeem'd as dreadful to the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> as it has ſince prov'd fatal. If this be true, as it is eaſie to be prov'd, then certainly <hi>Danby</hi> had ſo much the more reaſon to wiſh him out of the way, than any Papiſt; who could fear him no more than any other Magiſtrate left behind, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Witneſſes of the Plot ſurvive to ſwear the ſame before others, as they had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: But being made away, none ſurvived who could with the like Authority make appear to the King and Kingdom the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s Treachery, in tampering ſo long with, and concealing a Matter ſo dangerous to both, as the Plot (whether true or falſe) muſt of neceſſity have proved.</p>
            <p>To leave then the firſt Head, we will come to the ſecond, Whether it was not in his power to put in execution his pleaſure therein; and that I am confident none will deny, who conſiders the mighty Authority he had at that time ingroſs'd, to which all men were forc'd to buckle, and for fear of which, Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> after divers bitter expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſevere reproofs, of medling too much with Perſons and Affairs about him, and the like, was forc'd (notwithſtanding his known fortitude) to court, attend, and make friends to be heard by him, in hopes of mollifying that anger he had reaſon to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of, knowing that he, who hazarded Kingdoms, would not ſpare private men for his purpoſe: This muſt needs be the true cauſe of all his fears and apprehenſions, expreſs'd to ſeveral Perſons of Quality and others, from the time of his complaints, which was then when he was disfavoured by <hi>Danby;</hi> and when he had in all appearance (if not obliged the Papiſte, yet) beeen as fair and equal to them, as any perſon in his ſtation. But ſuppoſing they joyned in his Murder, the benefit to be raiſed hereby was certain to be more the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s then theirs; ſo that to contrive it, was meer infatuation in them, but in him a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153044:2"/>mighty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Diabolical Policy, which by Sir <hi>Edmundbury</hi>'s firſt attendance was much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him to compaſs, than for them who are ſworn to have a long time, under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Stratagems, to bring about that, which was the worſt miſchief to their Cauſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> have thought of in the world. But when it ſhall be throughly conſider'd, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>knowledg'd to have been with the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> at his houſe, after one a clock that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid to be murther'd, and perhaps could be proved at the Lady <hi>Cook</hi>'s Chamber at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lock, was he not then more in the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s power, than in mens, who were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſworn) forc'd to let him go from an unknown houſe by St. <hi>Clement</hi>'s, and by a wile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him into <hi>Somerſet-Houſe-Yard,</hi> there to receive his death. This, I ſuppoſe, will make any indifferent perſon conclude, it was more the intereſt, and more in his power to deſtroy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han all the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> who are ſaid not to have any confederacy with him for the doing of it.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be conſider'd is, Whether he was not willing to have this wicked Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on done, which plainly to prove (but by thoſe that did it) is impoſſible, and thoſe who have ſuffer'd for it, ſay nothing of the matter. Nor muſt we rely altogether on what the Evidence ſay, ſince a great part they ſpoke to is by hear-ſay of others; or of the particular paſſages at and after his death; and not much as yet to the contrivance of it: Nay, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is as eaſie to contradict what is eaſie to be prov'd, <hi>(viz)</hi> That he was at the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s Houſe ſo late that day.</p>
            <p>But let it, in God's Name, be examin'd, Whither Mr. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> carry'd him, when they took Water together at <hi>Whitehall;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Chriſtian, the L. Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Gentleman, with whom Sir <hi>E. G.</hi> took water at the Privie Stairs.</note> where he parted with him, and in what Company he left him; for that man breathing doth not yet appear, (except thoſe that ſay they were concern'd in his Murther) who ever ſaw him alive, after Mr. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and he were together that day. And it is ſtrange, a man ſo well known as he was, ſhould ſpend a whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and no man come to own the place he was in, for ſo many hours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> past between his being at the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s houſe, and the time he's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to enter into <hi>Somerſet-houſe</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> Can it be likely he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> out of his Enemies hands from the time that he remain'd inviſible, to the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ther? No ſurely. Let <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Ramſey</hi> be throughly examin'd, and preſsd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they kept him him all that time, what Jeſuits or others they confederated withal, to deliver or betray him to his Executioners, and where they themſelves ſpent their time that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> if this be done impartially, and things traced throughly, no doubt more will appear of the Murther and the Plot, than hath hitherto been reveal'd.</p>
            <p>It would be neceſſary to trace from Dr. <hi>Lloyd,</hi> who firſt was Author of what he was told, ſome hours before the diſcovery, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That he was found with his own Sword through his Body; and that Report too that he had two Wounds about him. Let this be done im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially, and ſuffer the honeſt Perſons (who like <hi>Daniel</hi> are zealous to diſcover the truth) be protected in their Enquiries, and no doubt all the wicked Inſtruments will be diſcover'd, to the glory of God, and the revenge of innocent Blood, which otherwiſe may cry for Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Land.</p>
            <p>NOw if you obſerve, the Author of this, be it who he will, does only point them out a way, to diſcover more of the great myſtery of Iniquity on foot, than had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider'd; which though the Houſe of Commons did not directly follow, yet upon ſcrutiny of many things therein, they found plainly theſe Particulars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> had held Correſpondence with <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Tongue,</hi> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Plot was diſcover'd to the King; that divers ſecret Meetings were between them at <hi>Fox-Hall,</hi> where, in the Almſ-houſe <hi>Oates</hi> and <hi>Tongue</hi> lodg'd, to be ready for their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> at an Inn kept by a Painter near to the Landing-place there. Theſe things being certain, they concluded, that either the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> was in the Plot, until he found it diſcover'd to the King, and then to ſave himſelf, fell on <hi>Coleman,</hi> and the reſt; or otherwiſe, that he was the original inventer of it, and procurer of Witneſſes, to involve the Nation in blood, and to ruine the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and deſtroy all the Papiſts, for purpoſes of his own; this made the Commons Reſolve on his Trial: For though they were ſufficiently allarm'd by the Plot, to provide new Laws againſt Popery, yet are they unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deſtroy Papiſts themſelves, (if innocent) that ſuch Blood might not cry for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the Nation. But if the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi> had been firſt try'd, then upon the proofs aforeſaid he muſt have made his defence, either averring the Plot to be true, and his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153044:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſhould have taken effect, by his concealing it ſo long, or that it was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> invention of his own; that he by falling on a Party ſuſpected before, and now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch horrid Crimes and new Deſigns, might juſtifie the keeping up of an Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> opinion of Parliament, and eſcape the Impeachment, he could not but expect at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Either of theſe defences muſt have enlightned the Commons in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt the Lords; for if they had been to be guilty by the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> joynt Conſpirator with them, then the Commons had had much ſafer proof to rely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they have by men, whoſe ill Lives formerly render them ſuſpected teſtimonies, ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> oft zealous againſt Popery, and perhaps by counter-Evidence prepared by the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> might have been fully ſet by as perjur'd men; or if he had owned the Plot, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> or any other Reaſons, then had he naturally cleared ſuch of the Five Lords, as had not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> parties perhaps with him in the Murther of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey,</hi> which the foregoing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per lays ſo cloſe at his door. This is the true cauſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Commons adhering to their Vote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and upon the whole cannot but be commended by all good men, and conſequently their ſuddden breaking off, is a trouble to all, who have no deſign but the diſcovery of truth; and I find the Papiſts themſelves have the moſt dreadful apprehenſions of it, knowing that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the receſs, 'tis their Blood will be the pledge given to the People, of their pretended zeal againſt Popery, who have had power to obſtruct Juſtice againſt the Earl of <hi>Danby.</hi> But I am confident ſuch proceedings will find a ſuitable return; for though ſome few of the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for ſome time are gull'd, yet will ſuch cruel Councils be deteſted by all thinking men, when they ſee only thoſe men deſtroy'd, whoſe blind zeal at worſt has made them Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals; and that not ſo much to puniſh them, as to blear the eyes of Juſtice, and to ſave the Man, who of all the World hath the moſt betray'd his Truſt, in correſponding with <hi>France</hi> to ſell the Honour of the Nation, which as plainly appears by his own Letters, as <hi>Coleman</hi>'s did by his, by Contrivances to eſtabliſh a ſtanding Army to enſlave us, his Practices to ſow diſcord in the Royal Family, his bribing of Commons in Parliament to betray that Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in them, and all other his viſible black Crimes, does plainly appear the worſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and the ruiner of his King and Countrey. I ſay, theſe things (let them be who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> adviſe them) threaten us with Judgement; from the coming of which upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> humbly offer up our prayers to the All-ſeeing God, from whom none of their ſecr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es are hid, who is able, and will at laſt, return all their Crimes into their own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in which day none will eſcape from his vengeance, but ſuch as from their ſouls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and preſerve their hearts and hands from ſeeking innocent Blood, and Malice, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be the true and conſtant Endeavour of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>urs.</hi> J B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
